Finding Aid for Suzanne Sareini papers, circa 1960-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Suzanne Sareini papers circa 1960-2013
Sareini, Suzanne.
1 oversize folder
2 oversize boxes
4 linear feet (in 5 boxes)
2015006 Aa 2; Ac
Arab-American Politician and businesswoman from Dearborn, Michigan, and first Arab American elected to Dearborn City Council. Personal materials related to her political campaigns, community involvement, and city council service, as well as restaurant business papers and menus, and menu's from the Dearborn restaurant community.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Suzanne Sareini (donor no. 11121 ) in June 2014.
The collection is open to research.
Suzanne Sareini is a Lebanese-American politician and business owner from Dearborn, Michigan. She was born to Houssain "Sam" Mallad and Skiney Mallad on May 4, 1951 in Dearborn and graduated from Fordson High School in 1969. Dearborn has the highest population by percentage of Arab-Americans in the country, and Ms. Sareini is a second generation member of this community. She is the mother of four children and a grandmother to fourteen.
Ms. Sareini was the first Arab-American (man or woman) to be elected to the Dearborn, Michigan City Council. She was first elected in 1989 and served six terms, retiring from the council as President Pro-Tem after 24 years when her final term expired at the end of 2013. While in office she was particularly interested in senior and youth issues and attracting development in Dearborn. During her tenure, Councilwoman Sareini was one of only a few practicing Muslims to hold any type of public office nationally. Her son, Michael Sareini, was elected to the City Council in 2013.
In addition to serving on Dearborn City Council, Ms. Sareini ran in 2010 as the Republican Party's candidate to represent district 15 in the Michigan House of Representatives, running on a platform of job creation and bipartisanship, but lost in the general election to George Darany, the democratic candidate.
Ms. Sareini is also an active member of the Republican Party in Michigan and nationally, and was appointed by Michigan Governor John Engler to the Arab American Advisory Committee, as well as the Michigan Women's Commission, serving two terms on each. She served as a delegate to the Republican National Convention in 1992 and was appointed by President George H.W. Bush to the U.S. Office of Personnel Management. Ms. Sareini also served as chairwoman of the National Arab-American Republican Heritage Council and as a member of the Michigan Republican Heritage Groups.
Councilwoman Sareini's father, Houssain "Sam" Mallad opened Uncle Sam's Restaurant, in 1964, which grew to become one of the most well-known Middle Eastern restaurants in the area. Ms. Sareini and her husband Tom took over the restaurant after the death of her father, and ran several iterations over the years under the names "Uncle Sam's Restaurant", "Uncle Sam's Village Café", and "The Village Café and The 19th Hole".
After "The Village Café and The 19th Hole" closed, Ms. Sareini has worked as a realtor in the Dearborn Community.
The collection is divided into two series, Political Career and Community Involvement and Restaurants.
The Suzanne Sareini Papers represent Ms. Sareini's involvement in the Dearborn community, her service on the Dearborn City Council, and her electoral campaigns for city council and state representative. Additionally represented are the restaurants owned by the Sareini family, and their role in the Dearborn restaurant community. This collection will be of particular interest to researchers interested in Dearborn politics and government, the Dearborn Arab-American community, and Dearborn restaurants in the 1990s and early 2000s.
Subjects:
Arab American women--Michigan--Dearborn.; Arab Americans--Michigan--Dearborn.; Dearborn (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Elections--Michigan--Dearborn.; Restaurants--Michigan--Dearborn.; Sareini, Suzanne.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
City council members--Michigan--Dearborn.; Political campaigns--Michigan--Dearborn.; Restaurants--Michigan--Dearborn.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Political Career and Community Involvement 1989-2013
  The Political Career and Community Involvement series (circa 1989-2013; 3.5 linear feet, 1 oversize box, and 1 oversize folder) contains records from Ms. Sareini's political service and involvement in Dearborn community groups. The political campaign materials include both Ms. Sareini's campaigns for city council from 1989 to 2009 and her state representative campaign in 2010 and consist of correspondence, campaign literature, planning and financial documents, election data and photographs. The materials from her service on city council include photographs, speeches, reports, correspondence, city publications (including several versions of the Dearborn City Charter), awards, and a map of Dearborn with classifications of the streets and highways published by the Department of Public Works in 1986. Community involvement consists of materials from the Michigan Women's Commission, the Republican Party, and the Arab American community. The Newspapers and clippings subseries includes whole issues and selected articles from regional and local publications in Arabic and English. The majority are from the Dearborn Times Herald and the Dearborn Press & Guide, with a few issues each of the Arab-American News, the Detroit News, The Detroit Free Press, and a few other local publications.
  - Political Campaigns
    - Dearborn City Council: Correspondence, Campaign Plans, Photographs, Election Data, etc. 1989-2010, 10 folders (Box 1)
    - Michigan House of Representatives) 2010, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Community Involvement, circa 1995-2005, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - City Council
    - Correspondence, Speeches, Photographs, Reports, and Awards 1989-2011, 10 folders (Box 2)
    - Dearborn city documents 1994-2009, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Public Works Map of Dearborn Road Classifications 1986 (Folder 1)
    - Awards 2001-2002 (Box 6)
      (oversize)
  - Newspapers and clippings
    - Dearborn Times-Herald, 1993-2011 (Box 4)
    - Dearborn Press & Guide, 1993-2011 (Box 5)
    - Detroit News, Detroit Free Press, Arabic publications, and other local publications, 1993-2011, 3 oversize folders (Box 6)
- Restaurants 1960-2000
  The Restaurants series (circa 1960-2000; 0.5 linear feet and one oversize box) contains two subseries, Sareini Family Restaurants and the Dearborn Community Restaurant Menus. The materials from the Sareini family restaurants, including Uncle Sam's Restaurant, Uncle Sam's Village Café, and The Village Café and the 19th Hole, consist of business papers and some recipes, photographs of the restaurant and performers, and various menus from each iteration of the restaurant. The materials from the Dearborn restaurant community consists of menus from several dozen restaurants around Dearborn representing many different types of cuisines that existed in Dearborn in the 1990s.
  - Sareini Family Restaurants
    - Papers, menus, and photographs circa 1960-2005, 9 folders (Box 3)
    - Oversize Menus and Photographs circa 1970-2000 (Box 7)
      (3 oversize folders)
  - Dearborn Restaurant Community Menus
    - circa 1990-2000, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Oversize menus circa 1990-2000 (Box 7)